Let's start with a dirty word, shall we?
Pandemic.
As we transition out of the last
pandemic, we're entering a new pandemic
of addiction that might be the most
pervasive addiction in human history.
Scary part is, the world has yet to even
acknowledge that this addiction exists,
despite it being all around us and
fueling our current mental health
crisis.
But today,
we turn the tide on this new addiction.
What if I were to tell you that in 2007,
a new addictive drug came out and it
took the world by storm?
In less than 15 years, over half of the
world's population was using this drug
daily.
It was causing a rise in depression,
anxiety, and suicide in all age ranges,
but especially in young girls.
And it was accounting for 3,000 traffic
deaths per year in the United States
from impaired driving.
If this were happening,
wouldn't there be an outrage?
Wouldn't the government and society as a
whole be trying to fix this?
Wouldn't we be drafting class action
lawsuits and demanding justice?
Well,
check your pockets.
Cuz I'm guessing you have this drug on
you right now.
And it's your smartphone.
When you think about addiction, what
comes to mind?
Substances like drugs and alcohol? Maybe
sex, gambling?
You think about computer code?
Apps?
Algorithms?
As a child and adolescent psychiatry
fellow, I am here to advocate for my
patients, who are mostly kids age 5 to
19, who I'm seeing become addicted to
their phones in mass. And the purpose of
this talk is to shift your perception of
addiction because we must start viewing
smartphones, technology, and social
media in the context of addiction if we
want to reverse our current mental
health crisis.
What we know about addictions,
neurologically, is that all addictive
things, including your smartphone,
increase dopamine in your brain at the
levels of the tegmental ventral
tegmental area and the nucleus
accumbens.
Dopamine makes you feel good, satisfied,
but also increases your drive.
That drive is important cuz it's the
drive that makes you do things over and
over again.
For example, in caveman times, if you
were find a new food source that helped
you survive, say a big bush of wild
blueberries, your brain would release a
ton of dopamine to make you feel good
about your find and increase that drive
to do it again.
In today's world, there are endless apps
that are trying to trick your brain into
releasing dopamine without being
fundamentally good for you.
App developers have found a way to hack
our reward and addiction pathway and
they did it without a substance.
They did it with computer code.
Addiction in 2022 has become nothing
more than zeros and ones.
Typically, we define addiction by these
signs. Play along and see how many you
have. Like hazardous use, using while
driving or when it's dangerous,
impaired social functioning, like
isolating yourself or giving up on your
social roles,
having withdrawal from your phone,
cravings for your phone, increased
tolerance, like your screen time
creeping up, trying to cut down on your
use and being unable to, spending more
time using than you initially
anticipated, and giving up your hobbies
and interests to use.
How many of you have that
"Oh, crap. That's me." feeling?
And if you don't see it in yourself, how
many people around you do you see these
signs in?
So, if we're seeing everyone become
addicted to their phone, you'd think
that the mental health community would
be doing something about this, right?
But,
this addiction came on so fast that
academia has yet to catch up.
And as of now, none of the top mental
health associations in the world have
even recognized this as a real
diagnosis.
The DSM-5, the diagnostic and
statistical manual, psychiatry's Bible,
has no official diagnosis for phone
addiction.
The ICD-10 and 11, the international
billing and coding system we use in
America.
Now, there is a code for getting sucked
up into a jet engine and requiring
medical care,
but there's no code for phone addiction.
If there's no code, it makes it
incredibly difficult to diagnose, bill
for, and track.
We have to come to a consensus on a
diagnosis and a code, because right now,
without an official diagnosis, the world
has yet to even admit that this is a
real problem.
And you don't have to be a psychiatrist
to know that the first step in treating
an addiction is admitting that you have
a problem.
How pervasive is this issue? Well, to
compare it to smoking, at the peak of
the tobacco industry in 1954,
only 45% of Americans smoked.
Right now, 97%
of Americans have a smartphone, and
surveys indicate about half of them feel
addicted to them already.
Here's why your smartphone is a super
addiction. It places multiple addictive
elements into one device.
Video games, pornography, sports
gambling, shopping, social media,
instant messaging. By placing these all
into one device that lives in your
pocket, you're walking around with an
addiction ticking time bomb that you
have
unlimited access to.
Your phone is programmed to buzz and
ding you at just the right rate to make
sure that you're constantly thinking
about your phone and your screen time
creeps up.
Now, the phones are specifically
designed to be addictive, but there are
so many other reasons why this is a
super addiction.
Like rapid acceptance.
Remember, phones smartphones have only
been around for the past 15 years. The
iPhone was released in 2007.
And in 2022, 95% of American teens have
a smartphone and use them on average up
to 9 hours per day.
The original telephone took over 100
years to democratize
where everyone has access to it. The
smartphone did it in less than a fifth
of the time.
Smartphones have revolutionized a very
sexy topic in 2022.
Supply chains.
Most addictions have to be planted,
grown, processed, shipped, packaged,
prepared, and consumed.
Smartphones eliminate almost
all of these steps and allow app
developers to deliver free, legal,
addictive content to anyone
anywhere
instantly.
Imagine if there was a physical drug
that was free, legal, addictive, and put
right in your pocket whenever you craved
it.
How many people would be using it?
Smartphones will continue to evolve at
the pace of the internet age, quickly
and continuously.
Look how fast TikTok was able to take
over for an entire young generation.
That's because it was specifically
designed to be more addictive, designed
to be harder to put down.
This will keep on happening where every
few weeks newer, more addictive apps
will come out to replace their
watered-down predecessors.
But perhaps the most important reason
why smartphones are a super addiction
is because it's socially acceptable.
It's typically frowned upon to give your
kids smokes, booze, and porn.
But
giving your kids the new iPhone for
Christmas makes you a good parent,
right?
At least that's what the commercials
tell us.
I would argue that the phone is worse,
but society doesn't see it that way. And
that's why we've all been caught up in
this current of addiction with little or
no resistance from us.
So I hope by now I've convinced you that
your smartphone might be just a little
bit addictive.
The thing that worries me the most as a
mental health provider is
addictions have what we call
comorbidities or other mental health
problems that go with the addiction.
Depression, anxiety, substance use,
obsessive-compulsive disorder have all
been studied and found linked
to excessive smartphone use.
Not to mention the social problems that
are coming as a result. As I know lots
of kids who get two to three messages
per day telling them that they're
worthless
and that they should go kill themselves.
Kids face constant judgment from online
and social media, which I think might be
making social anxiety worse.
Sexual predation is rampant and
psychologically scarring an entire
generation.
You want to know how bad this problem
is? Ask any teenage girl how many times
she's been pressured for nudes.
The longer we let smartphone addiction
go on, the worse these issues will
become, especially in this next
generation who's growing up with an
addiction.
Because when your brain develops with an
addiction, the changes to brain
physiology and personality can be
dramatic.
And I'm not just talking about the very
young, as brain development is complete
in the early 20s for females and the
mid-20s for males.
Addiction literally rewires your brain.
We've all heard the stories about
someone addicted to methamphetamine or
heroin who lies, cheats, and steals from
their family to support their drug
addiction and ruins their relationships
in the process.
I have met young people who impulsively
steal credit cards from anyone they can
to support their online video game
addiction.
Similarly ruining their relationship and
trust with their family.
When your brain develops with an
addiction,
everything else comes second.
The rates of those comorbidities I
mentioned go up, academic performance
goes down.
Imagine how much creativity, empathy,
productivity, and connectivity we will
lose if everyone in society is on their
phone for 9 hours every day.
My training as a child psychiatrist has
taught me that in the very young, brain
development is dependent upon those
daily interactions with caregivers. And
babies these days are having to compete
with smartphones for the attention of
their parents.
Let's face it. Screens have
fundamentally changed parenting.
Directly in how much kids are on their
screens and indirectly by how much their
parents are on their screens.
I wonder as to how many collective hours
of that brain development, of that
interaction, we have lost because
parents are spending hours a day on
their phone just
scrolling.
This is a topic of personal interest to
me
as I'm going to be a first-time father
in 2023.
Thank you.
Right now, my screen time app tells me
I'm on my phone from 3 to 5 hours per
day.
And I'm curious as to how that will
change me as a person and as a a
I think it's safe to say that cutting
back on my phone use would give me more
of that interaction time with my child,
would make me a better parent, but to be
honest with you, I don't know if I can.
Cuz I've tried before
and I failed.
But,
I'm going to keep on trying.
Because we all have a social obligation
to make a world that we want my son,
your children, your grandchildren to
grow up in.
A world where a kid can go back to being
a kid.
Where 2-year-olds aren't handed an
addiction that consumes a third of their
entire existence.
A world with less depression, anxiety,
and suicide.
We have to take a hard look at our
relationships with our phones.
Cuz honestly, and you might not believe
this,
I'm not saying that smartphones are a
bad thing.
They're a wonderful tool in many cases.
And getting rid of them altogether is
just not realistic.
I'm saying that we have to have a
healthy balance with our phones before
we fall too deeply into this addiction.
So,
what do we do about it?
Here are four things you can do to
reduce problematic use in young people.
Number one, set screen time limiting
apps and set a password. Kids aren't
dumb, they'll just turn them off and
they do all the time.
Number two, take their phone away at
night.
Sleep is imperative to mental health and
brain development. And too many kids
these days are staying up all night on
their phone when they should be
sleeping.
Number three, talk to your kids about
this. Education is an important piece.
If kids know it's addictive and it's not
very good for them, they're less likely
to start.
And number four,
take a look in the mirror.
We have to set a good example for our
young people. We cannot expect them to
make a change if we ourselves are
unwilling to make a change.
Those are some of the individual things
you can do to stop the bleeding, if you
will, on this addiction.
The mental health community and the
medical community have some work to do,
too.
Like I mentioned earlier, got to come to
a consensus on that code and the
diagnosis.
We have to start raising awareness about
this. We have to start being diligent
about asking our patients about their
digital media consumption and screening
for signs of addiction.
But perhaps the most important thing we
can all do as a society is
hold the tech companies accountable for
what they're doing.
Cuz if we don't,
they're just going to keep on doing it.
Good news is, we were able to hold the
the tobacco companies accountable and
that helped turn the tide in the smoking
epidemic.
We can do the same thing now.
And I don't want to villainize the tech
industry too much, cuz I think there's a
real wonderful opportunity for
collaboration moving forward.
Imagine a world in which the tech
industry shares their data with
researchers so that we can understand
this addiction and reverse it.
And
what if we're also able to use that data
to be able to identify people at the
beginning stages of depression, anxiety,
ADHD, bipolar disorder, schizophrenia,
to make sure that those people get the
right help sooner.
The tech companies would go from being a
part of a problem to being a part of the
broader solution.
What a redemption.
Okay. I know this is a little
overwhelming and it's supposed to be.
We're nowhere near those long-term
research-driven solutions.
Today's journey starts with raising
awareness to an issue that's been right
in front of our eyes for the past 15
years.
That smartphone addiction is real.
And turning the tide on this new
pandemic starts right now.